Samuel Proger Papers MS221
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Samuel Proger Papers
1930 -- 1990
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Pratt Clinic/New England Center Hospital
Proger, Samuel
Boston Dispensary
MS221
5.3 Linear Feet
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 7 series: Legacy collection documentation; Correspondence; General files; Written works; Sound recordings; Artifacts; and Work files.
Custodial History
This collection was originally part of the archives of the New England Medical Center (NEMC), which closed in 1990. The collection was processed by Dave Nathan, archivist at the NEMC archives, in June 1989, and had the following NEMC acquisition numbers: 84-23, 84-26, 84-37, 85-33, 86-43, 87-18, 87-20, 87-21, 87-29, 89-1, 89-2.
In spring 2013, NEMC material was transferred from NEMC to a restoration company for conservation treatment, and was then transferred to off-site storage in custody of Digital Collections and Archives (DCA). In December 2014 and January 2015, the material was transferred to DCA for processing. Some material originally in the NEMC archives was not transferred to DCA, due to either poor condition or loss.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, subject files, and written works by and about Dr. Samuel Proger. A large portion of this collection comprises Dr. Proger's notes from various research endeavors, including his published works, such as The Medicated Society, and unpublished works. Also included in this collection are correspondence to and from Dr. Proger and physicians, as well as an award for his achievements at the New England Medical Center. A wealth of research regarding primary medical care is also included in the Correspondence series. Articles published in medical journals and speeches given at medical conferences, as well as some of his other research notes, are documented in the General files series. Administrative reports are included in the Work files series. The physical collection documentation folder of this collection includes copies of Dave Nathan's original finding aids as well as copies of the original acquisition records.
This collection suffered extensive water damage due to a flood before it was in the custody of DCA. It underwent conservation efforts before processing, but several materials, particularly folders, scrapbooks, and bound volumes, are still warped or retain a musty odor. In addition, almost of the material is in fragile condition, and must be handled carefully.
Consult the Photographs and audiovisual materials series of the New England Medical Center records (MS099.001) for images of Dr. Proger. In addition, the Pratt Clinic/New England Center records (MS222) contain material by Dr. Proger, as he worked closely with Dr. Pratt in expanding the hospital.
Related Materials
MS099, New England Medical Center records, DCA
Dave Nathan transferred images of Dr. Proger to the Visual Materials collection at the New England Medical Center archives in 1989 -- and T-NEMC photographs are now located in the Photographs and audiovisual materials series of the New England Medical Center records (MS099.001).
MS222, Pratt Clinic/New England Center Hospital records, DCA
As Dr. Proger worked closely with Joseph Pratt to expand the PC, material created by him may be found in this collection.
MS214, Boston Dispensary records, DCA
MS224, Tufts-New England Medical Center records, DCA
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Proger., M.D. was born on January 21, 1906. He received his MD in 1929 from Emory University, the same year he married Evelyn Levinson. Following graduation he moved to Massachusetts to work with Joseph H. Pratt at the Boston Dispensary (BD) for a year's residency. He also completed fellowships at University of Heidelberg and Tufts College School of Medicine, where he worked in cardiology.
In addition to his physician duties and research, Dr. Proger played a critical role in the development of the New England Medical Center (NEMC). NEMC was established in 1930 as an overseer to individual medical institutions in Boston, including the BD, the Boston Floating Hospital for Infants and Children (BFH), and the Pratt Clinic/New England Center Hospital (PC/NECH). Under Proger's guidance and tireless efforts, these institutions -- which, under NEMC, retained their own management structures, -- were integrated into a unified medical unit that partnered with the Tufts University School of Medicine.
After completing his fellowship at the School of Medicine, he was appointed Physician-In-Chief of the BD's diagnostic ward, a 20-bed unit established in 1931. The Great Depression left the BD financially strained, so Dr. Proger, along with Dr. Pratt, facilitated the opening of the Joseph Pratt Diagnostic Hospital in 1938, a 100-bed diagnostic facility. Unlike a general hospital, the diagnostic hospital took on a more holistic approach. Dr. Proger recruited international doctors and faculty for the PC, as well as soliciting financial gifts via the Bingham program. This not only helped expand the PC, but also further develop a regional medical program in the United States. Though the BD, BFH, and Tufts College School of Medicine had signed an agreement to be run under the auspices of NEMC, the opening of the Pratt Clinic in 1938 was the catalyst for not only the integration of these institutions and their partnership with Tufts University, but also the approach to primary medical care in the United States.
This practice was augmented by the Bingham Associates Fund of Maine, of which Proger was one of its leaders. The Fund's goal was to modernize medical care in the state of Maine using the resources at NEMC and the Tufts College School of Medicine. Under Proger's leadership, the BAF provided medical scholarships, supported continuing education, and funded diagnostic referral services. Dr. Proger also promoted the development of research and clinical laboratory programs.
In addition to his administrative accomplishments at NEMC, Dr. Proger was appointed chair of the Department of Medicine. He held these dual positions from 1948 until his retirement in 1971. He also made contributions to cardiology research. He pointed out the dangers of obesity in relationship to heart disease, and the relationship between blood fats, blood coagulation and effects on hardening of the arteries. These accomplishments were recognized with his appointments as president of the Massachusetts Heart Association and New England Cardiovascular Society.
Courtesy of his financial prowess and strong relationship with his patients, he was able to cultivate financial gifts which established the Ziskind Research Building, the Farnsworth Surgical Wing, the Biewend Building, and the Tupper Building, all facilities on the New England Medical Center campus. During his tenure, he also served in various capacities on the Board of Governors and Board of Trustees.
He was known not only for his recruitment of academics and clinicians, but also for being a role model to students for his high regard for ethics and patient relationships. His numerous contributions to administration, teaching, and patient care were honored with the opening of the Proger Health Services Building. Dr. Proger died in 1984.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Proger, Samuel, 1906-1984; Tufts Medical Center; New England Medical Center; Tufts-New England Medical Center; Boston Dispensary; New England Medical Center Hospital; Pratt Diagnostic Clinic; Tufts College. Medical School; Tufts University. School of Medicine; Pratt, Joseph H. (Joseph Hersey), 1872-1956; Cardiology; Primary health care; Primary care (Medicine); Medical care; Faculty papers; University history; Hospitals--Medical staff; Medicine -- History; Medical history
- Legacy collection documentation, 1990; MS221.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the finding aids by NEMC archivist Dave Nathan, as well as NEMC acquisition records.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Legacy collection documentation folder, 1990; MS221.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1930 -- 1984; MS221.002; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series primarily contains correspondence to and from Dr. Proger. Also included are newspaper clippings, published articles, and research notes related to Dr. Proger's professional work in primary care, and compiled publications of NEMC's Endocrine Laboratories. Pages are in fragile condition, and must be handled carefully.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically. While some folders are devoted to a single individual, others are grouped by alphabetical range.
  - Ben Gurion University of the Negev, 1979 -- 1982; MS221.002.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Bingham, William II, 1939 -- 1947; MS221.002.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Boston Medical Library - Trustee, 1979 -- 1982; MS221.002.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - C miscellaneous, 1969 -- 1983; MS221.002.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence on the publications of A Career in Primary Care, 1976; MS221.002.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence on the published monograph A Career in Primary Care, 1976 -- 1977; MS221.002.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - D miscellaneous, 1968 -- 1982; MS221.002.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Daedalus, 1974; MS221.002.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Davidson, Robert, 1972 -- 1980; MS221.002.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Davidson, Sidney, 1972 -- 1978; MS221.002.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Doctor and Teacher, Hospital Chief, 1982; MS221.002.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Duffy - London, 1973; MS221.002.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - E miscellaneous, 1967 -- 1983; MS221.002.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - F miscelleanous, 1968 -- 1983; MS221.002.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Fries, Almer, 1973 -- 1974; MS221.002.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - G miscellaneous, 1971 -- 1983; MS221.002.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - Gould Academy, 1973 -- 1982; MS221.002.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - H miscellaneous, 1963 -- 1974; MS221.002.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - H.E.W., 1972 -- 1974; MS221.002.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - Health care, 1973; MS221.002.001.00021 (Box 1)
  - Hebrew University, 1970 -- 1972; MS221.002.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - HMOs, 1978; MS221.002.001.00023 (Box 1)
  - Howard Johnson Foundation, 1962 -- 1979; MS221.002.001.00024 (Box 1)
  - I miscellaneous, 1971 -- 1983; MS221.002.001.00025 (Box 1)
  - Institute on Primary Care, 1974; MS221.002.001.00026 (Box 1)
  - J miscellaneous, 1974 -- 1983; MS221.002.001.00027 (Box 1)
  - K miscellaneous, 1961 -- 1984; MS221.002.001.00028 (Box 1)
  - L miscellaneous, 1968 -- 1983; MS221.002.001.00029 (Box 1)
  - Letters received, 1930 -- 1948; MS221.002.001.00030 (Box 1)
  - Papers, clippings, correspondence, 1947 -- 1976; MS221.002.001.00031 (Box 1)
  - Primary care (1 of 3), MS221.002.001.00032 (Box 1)
  - Primary care (2 of 3), MS221.002.001.00033 (Box 1)
  - Primary care (3 of 3), MS221.002.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Primary medical care, MS221.002.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Publications - Endocrine Laboratories, 1945 -- 1952; MS221.002.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Publications - Endocrine Laboratories, 1952 -- 1955; MS221.002.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Publications - Endocrine Laboratories, 1956 -- 1959; MS221.002.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Publications - Endocrine Laboratories, 1960 -- 1964; MS221.002.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Publications - Endocrine Laboratories, 1965 -- 1969; MS221.002.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Regarding publication of Doctor and Teacher, Hospital Chief, 1982; MS221.002.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Robert, 1983; MS221.002.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Tupper, Earl, 1961 -- 1966; MS221.002.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Tupper, Glenn, 1966 -- 1984; MS221.002.002.00012 (Box 2)
- General files, 1946 -- 1983; MS221.003; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains medical journal articles, some administrative reports, and some correspondence.
  According to Dave Nathan's Guide to the NEMC Archives, the following items are missing:
  Minutes of the Board and various committees, 1978-1984.
  Reports of the Board and various committees, 1966-1968, 1983-1984.
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
  - Proger building dedication, 1973; MS221.002.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - 6th Aaron Thurman lecture, 1980 -- 1981; MS221.003.002.00013 (Box 2)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges, 1951; MS221.003.002.00014 (Box 2)
  - BAF student seminar, 1962; MS221.003.002.00015 (Box 2)
  - Boston City Hospital symposium, 1973; MS221.003.002.00016 (Box 2)
  - Cardiovascular research, 1948 -- 1979; MS221.003.002.00017 (Box 2)
  - Cincinnati, 1976 -- 1983; MS221.003.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Complete Physician, 1947 -- 1953; MS221.003.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Diagnostician, 1951; MS221.003.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Distinguished chairman of medicine award, 1980 -- 1981; MS221.003.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Education and role of the healer in the third millenium, 1976; MS221.003.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Education of different types of physicians for different types of health care, 1970 -- 1972; MS221.003.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Eulogy for Dr. Edwin Bennett Astwood, 1976; MS221.003.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Evolving patterns of primary care, MS221.003.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Framingham talk, 1976; MS221.003.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Hexter lecture, 1971; MS221.003.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - J.A.M.A. Editorial, 1972; MS221.003.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Levy, Robert, 1982; MS221.003.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - Macmillan Company, 1967 -- 1973; MS221.003.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - Medical diagnosis before computers, 1974; MS221.003.003.00014 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina, 1976; MS221.003.003.00015 (Box 3)
  - Periodic checkups, 1975 -- 1978; MS221.003.003.00016 (Box 3)
  - Postgraduate division, 1964 -- 1971; MS221.003.003.00017 (Box 3)
  - Pratt, Joseph, 1956 -- 1977; MS221.003.003.00018 (Box 3)
    Contains some handwritten correspondence with Joseph Pratt.
  - Samuel Proger, MD., reference file, 1953 -- 1984; MS221.003.005.00040 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    75 years from date of creation.
    Clippings, correspondence, speeches, writings, testimonials, recommendations, offprints, a photo, and a nametag all by or relating to Samuel Proger.
  - Sexual activity and the postcoronary patient, 1968; MS221.003.003.00019 (Box 3)
  - Some effects of injected Cytochrome C in Myocardial and Cerebral Anoxia in man (Dekaneas), 1946; MS221.003.003.00020 (Box 3)
  - Some notes on Cytochrome C (Decaneas), 1947; MS221.003.003.00021 (Box 3)
  - Talk - Sullivan, John, 1976; MS221.003.003.00022 (Box 3)
  - Testimony - Quarles, John, 1974; MS221.003.003.00023 (Box 3)
  - Testimony - Weinstein, Louis, 1975; MS221.003.003.00024 (Box 3)
  - Tupperoller evaluation progress report, 1978; MS221.003.003.00025 (Box 3)
  - Veterans Administration Hospital grand rounds, 1958 -- 1970; MS221.003.003.00026 (Box 3)
- Written works, 1940 -- 1982; MS221.004; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains journal articles, research notes, and lectures given by Dr. Proger. Also included are two published works; one written by Proger, the other about him and his medical career. The unpublished works include a table of contents.
  According to Dave Nathan's Guide to the NEMC Archives, the following item is missing:
  Address: The Boston Dispensary, the Origin of the Tufts-New England Medical Center: A Historical Perspective, 1977.
  - Unpublished works (1 of 5), 1940 -- 1950; MS221.004.003.00027 (Box 3)
  - Unpublished works (2 of 5), 1950 -- 1960; MS221.004.003.00028 (Box 3)
  - Unpublished works (3 of 5), 1960 -- 1970; MS221.004.003.00029 (Box 3)
  - Unpublished works (4 of 5), 1972 -- 1980; MS221.004.003.00030 (Box 3)
  - Unpublished works (5 of 5), 1980 -- 1981; MS221.004.003.00031 (Box 3)
  - Medicated Society, The, 1968; MS221.004.003.00032; Proger, Samuel (Box 3)
  - Doctor and Teacher, Hospital Chief, 1982; MS221.004.003.00033; Black, Herbert (Box 3)
- Sound recordings, 1948 -- 1956; MS221.005; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains ten 33 rpm records of what is believed to be the proceedings of two building dedications, the Harry Posner Hall at the Tufts University School of Medicine and the Ziskind Research Facilities of the New England Medical Center.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Ziskind Research Facilities dedication (1 of 8), 1948; MS221.005.003.00034 (Box 4)
    phonograph record
  - Ziskind Research Facilities dedication (2 of 8), 1948; MS221.005.003.00035 (Box 4)
  - Ziskind Research Facilities dedication (3 of 8), 1948; MS221.005.003.00036 (Box 4)
  - Ziskind Research Facilities dedication (4 of 8), 1948; MS221.005.003.00037 (Box 4)
  - Ziskind Research Facilities dedication (5 of 8), 1948; MS221.005.003.00038 (Box 4)
  - Ziskind Research Facilities dedication (6 of 8), 1948; MS221.005.003.00039 (Box 4)
  - Ziskind Research Facilities dedication (7 of 8), 1948; MS221.005.003.00040 (Box 4)
  - Ziskind Research Facilities dedication (8 of 8), 1948; MS221.005.003.00041 (Box 4)
  - Harry Posner Hall dedication (1 of 2), 1956; MS221.005.003.00042 (Box 4)
    Sides 1 and 3.
  - Harry Posner Hall dedication (1 of 2), 1956; MS221.005.003.00043 (Box 4)
    Sides 2 and 4.
- Artifacts, 1980; MS221.006; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains an award given to Dr. Proger.
  According to Dave Nathan's Guide to the NEMC archives, the following item is missing:
  Portable EKG machine.
  - Distinguished chairman of medicine award, 1980; MS221.006.003.00044 (Box 3)
- Work files, 1952 -- 1984; MS221.007; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series primarily contains correspondence, but also contains medical journal articles and administrative reports related to the New England Medical Center and the Tufts University School of Medicine.
  General Addresses, 1951-1978
  Lectures, 1952-1978
  Grand Rounds, 1959-1968
  Symposiums, 1962-1976
  Post Graduate Medical Institute, 1964-1971
  Eulogies, 1962, 1976
  Testimonials, 1974-1975
  TV Program (BAF)
  - 200 Club, 1972; MS221.007.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - M miscellaneous, 1972 -- 1980; MS221.007.005.00002 (Box 5)
  - Massachusetts Department of Public Health, 1974; MS221.007.005.00003 (Box 5)
  - McCormack-Fitzgerald, 1954 -- 1957; MS221.007.005.00004 (Box 5)
  - N miscellaneous, 1981 -- 1983; MS221.007.005.00005 (Box 5)
  - National Advisory Committee for Ambulatory Care, 1975 -- 1978; MS221.007.005.00006 (Box 5)
  - National Geographic Society Dr. Charmichael, 1967 -- 1972; MS221.007.005.00007 (Box 5)
  - NEMC Audit Committee, MS221.007.005.00008 (Box 5)
  - NEMC Research and Patent Committee, 1980 -- 1982; MS221.007.005.00009 (Box 5)
  - NEMC Women's Research Center, 1981; MS221.007.005.00010 (Box 5)
  - New England Center Hospital department of Endocrinology, 1958 -- 1971; MS221.007.005.00011 (Box 5)
  - New England Center Hospital department of Neurology, Neuro-surgery, and Psychiatry, 1955 -- 1971; MS221.007.005.00012 (Box 5)
  - New England Journal of Medicine, 1956 -- 1984; MS221.007.005.00013 (Box 5)
  - New London, Connecticut, 1974; MS221.007.005.00014 (Box 5)
  - Nursing Development Program NEMC, 1982 -- 1983; MS221.007.005.00015 (Box 5)
  - P miscellaneous, 1952 -- 1974; MS221.007.005.00016 (Box 5)
  - Patient care seminar for managers, 1972 -- 1984; MS221.007.005.00017 (Box 5)
  - Quality assessment - BAF, 1975 -- 1979; MS221.007.005.00018 (Box 5)
  - Quality assurance, 1976 -- 1978; MS221.007.005.00019 (Box 5)
  - Quality assurance - incentives, 1975 -- 1978; MS221.007.005.00020 (Box 5)
  - R miscellaneous, 1968 -- 1977; MS221.007.005.00021 (Box 5)
  - Robert Schwartz Medical Offices: 35mm microfilm from Boston Building Department re: Hans Seelye specifications, 1971; MS221.007.005.00041 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Rounds Lemuel Shattuck Hospital, 1962; MS221.007.005.00022 (Box 5)
  - Ruck, estate of Frank, 1968; MS221.007.005.00023 (Box 5)
  - Salary committee report and correspondence, 1968 -- 1969; MS221.007.005.00024 (Box 5)
  - Search committee physician-in-chief, 1970 -- 1976; MS221.007.005.00025 (Box 5)
  - Strang Clinic, 1983; MS221.007.005.00026 (Box 5)
  - T Miscellaneous, 1968 -- 1983; MS221.007.005.00027 (Box 5)
  - Tufts campaign, 1981 -- 1983; MS221.007.005.00028 (Box 5)
  - Tufts Medical School 2nd year, 1969 -- 1970; MS221.007.005.00029 (Box 5)
  - Tufts Medical School Miscellaneous, 1971 -- 1984; MS221.007.005.00030 (Box 5)
  - Tufts University Eastern Maine Medical Center affiliation agreement, 1982; MS221.007.005.00031 (Box 5)
  - Tufts University School of Medicine 3rd year, 1968; MS221.007.005.00032 (Box 5)
  - Tufts-NEMC reorganization, MS221.007.005.00033 (Box 5)
  - TUSM student lectures, MS221.007.005.00034 (Box 5)
  - U miscellaneous, 1965 -- 1972; MS221.007.005.00035 (Box 5)
  - Upjohn achievement award, 1966; MS221.007.005.00036 (Box 5)
  - V miscellaneous, 1968 -- 1973; MS221.007.005.00037 (Box 5)
  - W miscellaneous, 1967 -- 1982; MS221.007.005.00038 (Box 5)
  - Williams, Greer, 1977 -- 1982; MS221.007.005.00039 (Box 5)